- Hey folks, and welcome
to the learn UI design
lesson on alignment.
Alignment is one of the
most important topics
in user interface design.
And that's why we are starting with it
in this fundamentals unit.
Alignment is also if I had to say
probably the most underrated
topic in UI design,
there are plenty of things written about
color and typography,
but very little written about alignments,
except through grids,
which we'll cover later
as sort of a special case.
Alignment is an extremely
important thing for making any app
appear clean, neat and simple.
But even if that's not your brand
of the app that you're working on,
even if you're working on
something with a different
more interesting brand,
you are still going to
be spending a ton of time
thinking about how to align
elements with each other,
so as to achieve a feeling of
maximal cleanness or neatness.
All right, today, we're
gonna be looking at a mobile
and a desktop version of the same project.
So let's just dive right in.
And here's our sample app.
This is for the alignment co,
it's just a kind of made up data table
of a very typical sort
of data heavy application
that you very well might
find yourself working on
for any clients or for your day job.
We're just gonna go through this app
and take all these elements,
which I've kind of pasted on scattershot,
and we're gonna clean
them up and talk about
how to align elements,
some of the edge cases
and interesting scenarios
that come up when you try and do that,
we'll look at the desktop version.
And then we have the
mobile version over here
that we'll get to in just a sec.
So let's just start with the upper left,
this is actually not even
a difficult place to start,
we've got the sidebar,
I'm gonna unlock this layer
here, Command+Shift+L.
And that's gonna allow me
to center at least this box
within the sidebar here.
So I'm just pressing option H,
which horizontally centers in Figma.
That's easy enough to do.
If I select these two,
I can do the same thing.
That deals with the
horizontal alignment nicely.
But I still want to have
these vertically looking good.
So I'm actually gonna do even spacing
around all three sides of this.
Let's just move it up here.
Do eight pixels on every side.
And now I can press a
similar hotkey in Figma,
I can say option V,
and that will technically
vertically center
these two elements.
But if you notice, the alignment code,
the text actually looks
a little bit higher
than it should be.
And this is probably one
of the most common mistakes
in alignment and UI design is this program
is naively centering by the
bounding box of the text.
And yet, if you look, the
text is not really centered
inside of its own bounding box.
Now, if we just wanted to get
this product out the door,
we could ignore that because
centering and CSS on the web
is gonna be the same way.
But if we wanted to really
be careful about things,
we might specify that actually
this should be a little bit lower.
Now we have a margin
of 12 pixels above this
and 11 pixels below the text.
And let's just zoom out
and see does that appear
a little bit more centered.
As usual, we fail left and fail right
until we find kind of the best value.
So that's what I think is the best value
to have that feeling vertically centered.
And so that's 12 pixels on
top and 11 on the bottom.
All right, now let's move on
to this side nav bar here.
The icons are gonna be easy enough to do,
it looks like they're already aligned.
But I can do Control+Command+Left to send,
to align them all on their left edges,
will make sure they have
a decent margin here,
maybe 16 pixels or so.
And we can have the same for the text.
And one thing we wanna do
here is have every text item
line up neatly with this particular icon.
Now, the way I calculated this,
each of these icons is 24 by 24 pixels.
And then there's well, in this case,
there's 19 pixels of space between them.
Let's actually just make
that a nice, easy 20
pixels a space.
Oh, it's not even so I can't see it.
But if I do distribute vertical spacing,
now I have 21, then I can go down to 20.
So that's even.
So between a 24 pixel tall icon
and the 20 pixels of
space below each of 'em,
each row so to speak has 44 pixels
of its own height that
it needs to take up.
And that happens to be the
line height of the text here.
So, I know these will
match up row over row.
And I'm just kind of generally
trying to eyeball centering here.
And that looks good.
Now this is already 44 pixels tall.
So I'm just going to center
it such that it makes the icon
and the text appear
like it's in the middle.
But I can use the icon
as a reference check.
Now we talked about above,
where if the bounding
box around some content
does not have the content
centered within it,
it's kind of gonna mess up
your centering alignment.
Any good icon set should have the icons
appear to be basically centered
within the bounding box.
So this is the feather icon set.
It's really high quality,
all of these,
I'm really just gonna trust
that they're gonna look good
right out of the box,
I'm gonna move this up one.
So that way we have the same
margin on all three sides here.
And then a little bit right there.
Awesome.
So far, this is looking much neater,
I'm gonna lock this sidebar in the place
'cause we're not gonna be
playing with that anymore.
And then let's align this
six with this project,
which is maybe saying that
there's six new projects
or something like that.
Now, this is size 15.
This is size 15.
So aligning text to the
same size is pretty easy,
you just need to align it at the baseline.
And actually, that applies
not only the text of
the exact same size, but even
if it's slightly different,
let's say, for instance, that
there were 26 new messages.
And we actually needed to have
this text be a little bit smaller,
that's really not a problem,
we would still try and align
things at the baseline.
And Figma, as it's currently implemented,
has text shrink from the
top not the baseline.
So I need to reposition it,
but it's overall not a big deal.
Again, we'll just have
some little margin here
that shows the 26th is
related to projects,
but give it some breathing room.
This sidebar is looking good.
The only last thing that
I wanna say about it
is beware because one common impulse
among beginning designers
is to try and align content
that is centered with content
that is say left aligned.
Now you might notice, hey,
this T right here doesn't really appear
aligned to the icons,
it doesn't really appear
aligned to that text,
just doesn't work so well.
You might say what if we
just indented these icons
so that they were actually
lined up with the T above here.
And I'm just kind of eyeballing it.
But you can imagine that could
be one way of doing this.
I strongly recommend against doing this.
What you should try and do is figure out
schemes of alignment that don't
rely on the specific widths
of any other elements on the page.
So for instance,
this text right here,
if this were text and it changed,
and I said the alignment company instead
and this were centered here,
then I would need to
change this margin here.
And that doesn't make much sense.
Another way to think about it is
if you translate it all the text
into a different language on the page,
you shouldn't have to
change any of the values
related to alignment.
So even though there could
be a slightly cleaner sense,
if this were say, maybe left aligned,
like I guess that would get
me a little more alignment.
But I wouldn't really want to do that.
Instead, I'm just gonna
deal with the fact that
this logo kind of demands to be centered,
this stuff demands to be left aligned,
and we're gonna leave those be.
All right, so now let's
move on to the main body
of the page.
Again, we'll just start at the top,
search bar is a great place to start.
Let's look here, it has a height of 42.
And this has a height of 44.
So maybe actually, what we'll do
is just give it a little
bit higher height here.
And that will allow us
to perfectly align it
with the little box in the sidebar.
Because this is a well designed icon set,
I'm just going to trust that the numbers,
it's gonna look good when
these numbers are all the same,
or at least the top and
bottom are the same.
Technically, this could
be a little bit off,
and it wouldn't be the
biggest deal in the world.
But it's always gonna appear neat
if I kind of have that even spacing.
Now, we talked about the
fact that Adelle Sans
is nice of a font as it is,
it doesn't sit vertically centered
within its own bounding box.
So we're gonna have to
kind of do this by eye,
there, that looks about centered to me.
And we'll talk a little bit more about
vertically centering text
and elements like icons
in just a minute.
So now we have to deal with
this little profile photo right here.
And probably the easiest
way to do this is to zoom in
and make him exactly the same height
as the element that he
needs to align with.
But this actually brings up
one interesting edge case
that you'll sometimes
stumble upon in UI design,
which is if you're ever
aligning an element
that say rectangular or flat on one side,
with an element that's a circle,
there's sort of this mismatch in terms of
how they hit their
bounding line of alignment.
If you look, this rectangular element,
every single pixel along this border,
along this top border is
on this line of alignment.
Whereas the circle only
touches the line of alignment
at this infinitesimally small point.
And so you might get this weird effect
where the circle actually
kind of looks too small
compared to the rectangle.
It doesn't seem very bad here.
And so I won't necessarily
do anything to fix it.
But know that it is an option
and an accepted practice in design
to make the circle a little bit bigger
so that it actually goes
past the line of alignment
on both sides.
But like I said, I probably
won't do that here.
I'll just keep this guy a normal size.
One interesting place where this idea
of rounding going a little bit further.
One interesting place
where this comes up a lot
is actually in typography itself.
If you zoom way in
on almost any professionally
designed font,
you'll notice that flat
letter forms hit the baseline
and stay there, exactly there.
Whereas rounded letter forms
go a little bit past it.
It's just one more
instance of that kind of
adjusting for the fact that
round shapes don't feel like
they touch the line of
alignment quite as much.
We'll just give these elements
a little spacing here.
16 pixels should do it.
Maybe I'll actually bring
this in a little bit closer.
And let's actually talk
about aligning this icon
with this text.
Because again, I could just
take the naive approach
and do that.
But if you ask me that
actually feels a little bit low
compared to where it could be.
And so how do you align some random icon
and in this case,
this is an icon where
I just drew this shape,
there is no bounding box that
is kind of a helpful guide
for how to align it.
How do I align this custom drawn icon
with this text right here,
you wanna use a strategy that
I call center of pixel mass.
And so what this implies
is, if all of this,
I'm gonna call it ink,
if all of this ink
or all these filled in pixels had weight,
where would the center of
mass of this piece of text be,
for instance, it wouldn't be down here,
because all the masses above it basically,
except for this cue,
it wouldn't be up here,
it wouldn't even necessarily
be in the middle,
halfway between the cap height right here
and the baseline right here,
because there's more ink
sort of below this line
than there is above it,
since all the lowercase
letters have this ink
kind of on the bottom half of the figure.
And they don't have so
much on the top, right.
So whatever the center of pixel mass is
is kind of biased a little
bit towards the bottom.
And with this icon,
the goal is to figure out
the center of pixel mass
for this icon and then line them up.
So for this icon,
the center pixel mass will actually be
not in the bottom half here,
'cause this is just one little point,
it'll probably be biased a little bit more
towards the top half,
because these things jet
out so far to the top.
So what we're gonna do then,
is just kind of put this
where it feels like
it's roughly lining up,
where there's equal amounts
of ink above and below,
so to speak.
Those who know physics know that I'm
butchering this a little bit.
And that actually appears
pretty good to me,
I'm gonna give it a little bit more
of its own space, though.
Awesome.
All right.
Now, when we go to align this,
we're gonna want to align it horizontally
with the edge of the page.
And actually, we're gonna
wanna do the same thing here.
And these two vertical
lines that bound the content
of the page on the left
and the right hand side
might be two of the most
important lines of alignment
that we're gonna do on this project.
Not only will they visually form sort of
some of the strongest lines
of alignment on the page,
but also, since this is a website,
and it can be viewed on screens
of many different sizes,
as this website gets bigger or smaller,
we're gonna need to know
right from the very beginning
of designing how exactly we
want this website to respond.
For instance, if this content,
if the content width would
just go from here to here.
So let's pretend all this content
just fit in the same width right here.
And then as the screen got bigger,
we have all of this stuff
continue to float in the middle,
where it had roughly an equal
margin on either side here,
or for instance, would
it stay anchored here,
or another possibility is
all of this content
would continue to grow,
and maybe this search bar would grow.
For what it's worth,
I don't recommend making a
search bar quite this wide.
But you get the idea,
you need to decide what
grows, is it for instance,
both margins, the margin on the
right or the content itself.
Now, that's ultimately something
we'll talk a lot more about in the lesson
on responsive design.
For now, we'll just pick one
scheme that works fairly well
for this size and stick with it.
So let's do something like
say a margin of 40 pixels
on the left hand side here.
And let's actually do
the same on the right.
This makes it fairly
straightforward to line up
some of the other elements,
which I'll just do super quick.
But we will come back to
each of these in turn.
Now, back to Ron Squire
up at the top here.
Now, we're running into
an interesting issue that
like responsive design strikes
only when we're doing digital design.
This is not something that
people designing posters
or flyers have to worry about.
And that is a hover state.
This Ron Squier, this is gonna be like
a little pulldown menu
with some settings or some
account stuff or whatever.
Just very typical pattern like that.
Right now however, there's nothing showing
that you can actually click on this.
And so when you hovered here,
we'd wanna show some sort of hover state
that makes it clear that yes,
you can click here and you're
gonna see whatever a menu
or something like that.
But now we have a little
bit of a conundrum
because if the hover state
actually goes beyond this icon,
then it's gonna stretch
past the line of alignment,
and it won't align with the stuff below.
However, if the hover state goes neatly to
the very line of alignment right here,
then these items would have
to be indented a little bit.
And just by default,
this is never going to align with this
unless you're hovering right here.
So what do you do?
Well, there's not necessarily
one solution here.
But if I was working on this project,
I would certainly think about giving this
a little bit more permanent of a display,
so that you never even
ran into that problem
in the first place.
Now that this button is here,
it makes me realize I
actually need to center these
perhaps a little bit better.
And then let's zoom out
and see how this looks.
Cool.
Feels like it'll work so far.
All right, let's move on to
this little title below here.
So this title is interesting,
'cause I've got users and then I have,
I mean, this would be account.
Clearly, there's not 203 of them.
But let's presume for a second.
And right now,
these are aligned by
baseline, which is good.
That's exactly how we wanna do it.
But when this text,
even though it's a little bit lighter,
you can see it's only 70% opacity here.
And this is bold.
And yet this is thinner, right?
It's a regular weight, it
still appears very heavy.
So I actually wanna make it
a little bit lighter somehow else.
Well, naturally, I could
go to adjust the size.
But if I adjust the size,
I'm gonna actually keep
the baseline aligned.
And I sort of had this choice of like,
what size do I actually
want to adjust it to?
Clearly, this feels a little bit small.
And then we saw that the other one was
too big to begin with.
One suggestion is we could
actually align the cap height
of the 203 with what's called the X height
of the word users,
it's called the X height, technically,
'cause it's the height of the lowercase X.
But it's also the height of a bunch
of other lowercase letters.
So don't ask me.
When we do that,
this actually buys us a
little bit more alignment
with this element right here.
And that's a huge plus.
One thing I want you to get the sense of
as you go through your own projects,
is trying to buy yourself
more feel of alignment
using the same elements.
A lot of times, you'll run into situations
where there's gonna be multiple
ways you can style things
or multiple ways you can do things.
Oftentimes, you'll want to
choose the way which gives you
a little bit more feel of alignment,
even though it's the exact
same elements on the page.
And that's what's going on here.
We didn't need to make this text
such that the cap height of
203 is equal to the X height
of the title here.
But by doing that,
we by ourselves just a
little bit more alignment.
Now this is simple,
this is gonna be kind of a
center of pixel mass style thing.
So vertically, I'm gonna
be aligning this with
somewhere just below the X height.
It's kind of a happy accident
that it actually looks
like the top of this icon
aligns with the X height.
But that's not necessarily intentional.
All right, cool.
This next bit should be super easy, right?
We're just going to
align all these things.
And let's give them a little
more even spacing here too,
14 is a bit much,
let's say maybe something like eight.
Same thing here, eight.
So this looks much better
with one exception,
this add users button is really big.
And why would I have made this big?
Well, ostensibly, it's
to draw attention to it.
And like fair enough, the size
does do that a little bit.
But there's other things
drawing attention to it too,
this is the only button that has an icon.
And probably the most eye
catching thing is that
this is blue,
whereas every other button
on the page is white.
So if I can make up for
needing to attract attention
using color and an icon,
that actually again,
allows me to buy myself a
little bit more alignment
by shrinking this down to size
with the other elements right here.
And in my opinion,
that is clearly the way to go.
I buy myself just a
little bit more alignment
with the same elements.
Now, it is worth mentioning
that braking alignment
to attract attention is
totally a valid strategy.
In fact, one of the classic cases of that
is what's called a floating action button,
which is a type of button
often for something like
adding a new element to the
page where it's circular here.
Actually, I realize I'm gonna
have to just create this over.
There we go.
Let's grab that.
And usually they have a
width somewhere around
say 50 or whatever.
And a shadow.
There we go.
Now, if this floating action button
was aligned with the table,
it might look like part of the table
or kind of be mistaken as
belonging to the table.
If you're gonna do a floating
action button like this,
by Google's own admission,
you really should break alignment
with the rest of the page
so that it attracts the most attention.
And technically, these things
should be anchored to the
bottom of the page as well.
But it's just tougher
to see whether or not
you're breaking alignment with the table
when it's way down here.
So something like that.
That's a very valid
excuse to break alignment,
and there are others.
All right, and now we
get to the table here.
So the table,
some of the elements within the table
should be fairly simple to align,
these things will be simply
left aligned, no problem,
let's come up with a little
bit of padding in here.
Well, maybe say 40 pixels of space
between the different rows,
Oh, I wanna point out something I did
even without thinking about it.
So notice, location, the
title for this column
is located directly above
the data for this column.
However, name, which sort
of covers both this image,
and the text name right here,
is located above the
text not above the image,
even if these belong to the same cell,
one thing I would want to
do is not align like this.
Because if you just
zoom out and look at it,
you'll notice it's actually a bit odd.
That kind of that feel of
alignment with this piece of text.
And then these four images
is not super strong.
But the feel of alignment
between this piece of text,
and these four pieces of
text is much stronger.
And there is actually a precedent
for this sort of thing in design.
Hanging punctuation is the centuries old
typographical tradition of
taking punctuation characters
like openings of quotes and parentheses,
and hanging them into the left margin
so that your text has as strong of a sense
of alignment as possible.
You can also do this with
things like bullet points,
or here on Charity Water's page,
if you scroll down,
you'll notice they
actually do it with icons.
So they didn't align this
icon with the text below it,
but instead have the icon
hanging off into the left margin.
That's essentially what we're doing here.
And I think it works perfectly.
Now, one other thing I'm gonna fix up here
is just align this,
and with uppercase text like this,
the center of pixel mass
really is truly halfway between
the cap height and the
baseline right here.
So I should be able to
center this fairly simply.
There we go.
I think that looks good.
Frankly, this could kind of go either way.
But I just wanna use
this opportunity to say
one other thing that might
be helpful, which is,
whenever you have an icon,
that sort of point here on one side
or anything you're trying to align this,
a little bit point here on one side,
that's the side that
should probably go closer
to the bounding box boundary.
So in this case, if we
know that we are aligning,
doesn't fit exactly.
But we're trying to center this
between these two red lines,
we will be closer to this side
than to this side overall,
simply because this side is point here,
this side has more mass.
And so the center pixel
mass is actually closer
to the center.
Awesome.
Now that looks good.
But there's one other thing
that I just wanna bring up
when working with things like tables.
So in a sense,
there's actually two lines of alignment
that you could align with this table,
there is the border between
the outside of the table
and the inside of the table.
But then there's also the border between
the inside of the table and
the first column of data.
And in some sense,
the border between the inside of the table
and the first column of the
data actually appears stronger.
And so you might think
maybe I should align that
with the content outside of the table.
And so here, now honestly,
this is maybe not the best example.
But frankly, the times
where you'd want to do this
are when the border between
the outside and the inside
of the element that has some
padding such as this table
are really difficult to see.
So when you zoom out,
there's really not a
lot of visual emphasis
on the transition from outside the table
to inside the table.
And the left edge of these images
is a more clear line of alignment
that you could then align
with the other content
on the page.
This problem can come up when
you're working with tables,
it can come up when
you're working with cards,
it can come up even sometimes
when you're working with buttons.
And overall, the best way to handle it
is to just align the padded
element like in this case,
the table and I say
padded because it has this
space between its outer edge
and where the content begins.
But the best strategy here
is to align to the outside
if that's what feels like the
strongest line of alignment.
So if this is say a hard white,
and then we could do other things too.
We could like give a shadow to this table.
And actually even that should be enough.
By adding a shadow and giving
it a hard white background,
it really becomes clear
that this is like a crisp
line right here,
which I can use to align to
the other content on the page.
Less so if I remove the shadow
and then I make the background
a little bit less opaque.
Now, the last detail I
wanna talk about here
is the fact that larger
text and smaller text
don't always align neatly, right,
you can see that this U,
even though it's
technically the word users
is at this line of alignment,
and so is the word newly added,
there's more of an indent before this U.
And the reason for that is
totally natural and unavoidable.
As the letter forms grow,
the space around the
letter forms grows as well.
And so if you really want to,
you can offset that a bit,
we can specify that this
title actually should be
just a little bit to the left
of the other text elements.
And that will make it feel
a little bit more aligned.
But that's a really fine detail,
and not necessarily
something most websites
would actually do.
I think this is looking pretty good.
And now we're gonna take a
quick look at the mobile version
of the same app.
So with mobile,
we're gonna be doing largely
the same sorts of things,
but it's actually pretty simplified.
Now, what I like to do
is always put on a ruler
at 16 pixels from the left edge
and 16 pixels from the right edge,
which should be 359 right here.
Currently, both Android and iOS specify
outer margins on the page
of exactly 16 pixels,
or points or whatever
unit you wanna call it.
So that's just a good
best practice to get into.
And then what we'll do is align
as much stuff as possible to those edges.
Lock this in place, move
this quite a bit closer,
we'll move the profile photo here.
If I wanted to I could
technically have it go past
since it's round.
But it's not honestly
a big deal in my mind.
And with vertically centering this icon,
it has a bounding box.
So the 12 pixels above and
below, that's pretty simple.
We'll just zoom out and take a look.
So far so good.
But we really will use these to align
some of the other elements on this page.
So maybe, for instance,
I'll put this here.
And our sort button will
have it kind of smashed up
against this button.
I suppose it's possible, I
could put it over here too,
like, I guess there's maybe
no problem with that per se.
But to me, it feels a bit weird.
These are just two
buttons that are related.
Even though, by the way,
like you might say, oh,
this sort button, this isn't
aligning with anything now.
Nothing else is on this line right here.
That's totally fine.
Because the way that
this gets its alignment
is it's aligned with this item right here.
For the sake of thinking about
things being aligned left
these two buttons function as one group,
and that's no problem.
All right.
So now we get to this list,
we have the text, which is
already pretty neatly aligned.
But I still need to do these images.
It's four of them, Control+Command+Left
to get them all align left,
we'll line them up here,
I'm gonna distribute
their vertical spacing
so that then I can deal with it here.
Now, each of these
images is 36 pixels tall,
and there's 18 pixels between them.
If I go to this text,
you can see I've just done
this all the primary list names
are in one layer and
all the secondary cities
are in another layer.
You don't have to do it this way.
But it's one way of doing it.
So I'm gonna add up the line height
plus the paragraph spacing
to figure out how tall each row should be,
24 plus 32, that's 56.
So I know that, if this is 36,
I want 20 pixels of space
between each of these images.
Let's go ahead and add that in.
I'll center them within
their box right here.
I'll highlight these text layers,
bring them on over a little bit.
And then kind of roughly
try and center them
with the images.
There we go.
That's looking good.
Now, one thing I also can do
to give a little more sense of alignment
or even clarification between list items,
is put in little divider lines
between the different
elements of the list.
So there we go.
I think those are all even
or they should be perfect.
Cool.
And notice one thing that's
probably worth calling out,
although we'll cover it
more in the lists unit,
is these lines don't actually
extend all the way here.
And it just happens to be
because when you see an image and a line
and an image and a line
and an image and a line,
it's just a little bit busier.
So, if the lines only
go as far as the text,
not only does it give a nice
strong sense of alignment
with that text,
but it also serves to kind of
divide one row from the other.
You don't have to do it like this.
And you could even do it where
these go a little bit beyond,
but not all the way to the image,
you have different options here.
Perfect.
So this alignment is looking good so far,
that covers the top of the page.
And now for the bottom of the page,
I'm gonna do the absolute standard,
which you really should
not be deviating from,
when you have an iPhone app,
or even an Android app,
where you have kind of some
navigational tabs at the bottom here,
you very much want to take
the width of the screen
divide it evenly into
the number of items here.
And then let, in this case,
each of these five items have one fifth
of the width of the screen.
So this frame here has a width of 375,
375 divided by 5 is 75.
I'm gonna highlight each
of these text layers,
you'll see why this is useful in a sec.
And I'm going to give
them a width of 75 pixels.
Then I'm gonna distribute
them horizontally
and put zero pixels of
spacing between them,
do Control+Command+Down to align them all.
And put them so that the
leftmost starts at zero pixels.
So now what I can do is go
and center each of these
with option H.
And of course, there's
still a bit of a mess.
Control+Command+Down
will align all of them.
And they're looking good.
The final concern about alignment
that I wanna mention has to
do with vertical centering.
Sometimes on mobile screens,
you'll have a lot of room to
vertically center something.
And oftentimes when that's the case,
you'll find that what looks the best
isn't necessarily what is
perfectly vertically centered.
So let's say we have,
so roughly 250 pixels
above the text and buttons
and then roughly 250 pixels below.
There we go.
Now it's 251 and 251.
And if you look at that,
or you showed it to someone
random and said, hey,
does this appear to be too
high or too low or just right?
Many people would say it appears to be
just a little bit too low.
And again, I don't know what
weird optical illusion this is.
But a lot of times when
you have the choice
of centering something in a larger space,
this is where it's most evident,
you should default or
bias towards having it
just be a little bit higher than lower.
So even going like this
highest seems to fix it.
Now, of course with this screen,
I don't even need to run into that issue,
I'd probably want these buttons down here
within thumbs reach,
I could have this up here even.
But if I'm gonna try and
center it in this empty space,
I'm probably gonna have a
little bit less room above
and a little bit more room below
so that it floats just a little high.
Again, this comes up the most
when you're looking at a
big screen and centering
within a bigger area.
But even in this very first example here,
when I saw that this text
appeared to be a little bit high.
It was kind of reassuring to me,
a lot of times if I have to make a choice
between being like just a
pixel high or a pixel low,
I will almost always
default in direction of
going one pixel up from what
might otherwise be perfectly centered.
All right, and that wraps
it up for alignment.
Thanks for watching.
So, if I had to drive home
the two most important lessons
from this video,
I would say first of all,
just align everything.
Basically every element on
your page should be aligned
with another element.
And this isn't hard.
I mean, consider first of
all that centering an element
within its parent container,
that counts as a form of alignment.
And we did that.
And even though we dealt with,
let's say 100 different
elements on those two pages,
it wasn't actually hard
to align any of them.
Like it was all pretty clear.
Nothing was really floating in space.
And that's by and large,
how it should be in your own designs,
everything is aligned with something.
The other element that I
wanna call your attention to
as this video ends is just to say,
play a little game with it.
Sometimes you'll run into cases
where you might style
things slightly differently.
Maybe there's way A and there's way B
and look at what might
buy you just a little bit
more feel of alignment,
even though it's just the
same number of elements,
what's gonna feel a little bit crisper
and cleaner and more well aligned.
And oftentimes little details like that
are the things that can bring
a design from good to great.
All right.
So all that being said,
take a look at the homework.
It's a file that you can download
and start playing around with.
Everything is done for you.
All you have to do is align some stuff
very much like this video, take a look.
I think you'll enjoy it and
post it in the student community
when you're done.
See you in the next video.